<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"><channel><title>Sam Feldstein</title><description>Sam Feldstein&apos;s personal website. Sam is a writer and web developer from Bondurant, IA.</description><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/</link><language>en-us</language><item><title>Things Make Sense</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/things-make-sense/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/things-make-sense/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Things make sense&lt;br /&gt;
because if they didn&apos;t&lt;br /&gt;
they wouldn&apos;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Unhealthy Skepticism</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/unhealthy-skepticism/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/unhealthy-skepticism/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ll see it&lt;br /&gt;
when I believe it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Who Writes Your Thoughts?</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/who-writes-your-thoughts/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/who-writes-your-thoughts/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Who writes your thoughts?&lt;br /&gt;
Presumably, you.&lt;br /&gt;
But how can you author a thought&lt;br /&gt;
before you have it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do that, you&apos;d have to know&lt;br /&gt;
what you were going to think&lt;br /&gt;
before you thought it.&lt;br /&gt;
And if you knew&lt;br /&gt;
what you were going to think&lt;br /&gt;
before you thought it,&lt;br /&gt;
you&apos;d have already thought it.&lt;br /&gt;
In that case, there would be no&lt;br /&gt;
before-the-thought&lt;br /&gt;
or after-the-thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there is a before-the-thought&lt;br /&gt;
and an after-the-thought.&lt;br /&gt;
Therefore, &quot;you&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
(in the sense that we mean)&lt;br /&gt;
can&apos;t have written the thought.&lt;br /&gt;
But if not &quot;you&quot;&lt;br /&gt;
who?&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>psychology</category><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Old Heavy Voices</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/old-heavy-voices/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/old-heavy-voices/</guid><description>Aging artists are in the process of succumbing.</description><pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In one of his books, I think &lt;a href=&quot;https://bookshop.org/p/books/adventures-in-the-screen-trade-a-personal-view-of-hollywood-and-screenwriting-william-goldman/10978223&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Adventures of the Screen Trade&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, William Goldman laments the tendency of artists&apos; abilities to deteriorate as they get older. But I think artists also gain something as they get older, and that something is gravitas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this is especially evident with singers. John Prine, Johnny Cash, Bob Dylan, Tanya Tucker, and John Hiatt come to mind. They sing the way your grandparents speak. You can feel the weight of their lives in the gravel of their voices. Maybe that gravel is just a byproduct of aging vocal cords, but I think it also suggests an existential symmetry: The older you get, the more you know; the more you know, the heavier things get; the heavier things get...and eventually you succumb.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I think makes these old voices so poignant is that they are all in the process of succumbing.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>art</category><category>music</category></item><item><title>My Problem With Programming</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/my-problem-with-programming/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/my-problem-with-programming/</guid><description>I like programming, but I don&apos;t know yet if it can tell me anything about how the world works.</description><pubDate>Sun, 09 Jun 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;How long have you been learning to code?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cumulatively, probably two to three years. I really got into it in October. And that&apos;s web development, what I mean when I say programming. First HTML and CSS, now I&apos;m learning JavaScript. Still not fluent in that, I wouldn&apos;t say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You like it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I do like it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what&apos;s the problem?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well so I do enjoy it, like I said. It is quite satisfying to build websites and see them work. But I can&apos;t get away from this sense that all I&apos;m learning how to do when I build websites is build websites. Does that make sense?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://scottaaronson.blog/&quot;&gt;Scott Aaronson&lt;/a&gt; put it a way in one of his posts. He said that he opted for quantum computing over programming because only one of those things was going to teach him anything about how the world worked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah. And you want to know how the world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right. And I can do that in my free time, of course, reading and so on. But we devote so much time to just trying to make a living that it would be nice if those efforts happened to also be teaching me about the nature of existence and not just how to tell computers what to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do you do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have two options as I see it. One is to drop coding and pursue something else. The problem there is that I don&apos;t know what I would drop coding for. Option two is to think critically about programming as a discipline and see if I might be wrong about whether or not I can learn something from it that might be relevant to life outside a computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which one do you like better?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The second. Because again, I don&apos;t know what I would do if I did drop coding, and I&apos;d like to get a real job sooner than later. And webdev happens to be one that I enjoy and also has the potential to pay well. And the other thing is I don&apos;t know that I&apos;m actually right about programming&apos;s potential to teach me anything about how the world works. There are plenty of programmers out there who are also philosophical. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulgraham.com/&quot;&gt;Paul Graham&lt;/a&gt; is a great example. But what I don&apos;t know is how much programming informs his view of things versus to what extent he&apos;s a programmer who just happens to also be interested in how the world works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Isn&apos;t he the one who defines programming as a mode of expression, like painting or sculpture?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He has defined it that way in one of his essays. He likens it to art in that yes, it&apos;s a mode of expression, which implies that it informs his perspective, because what are you expressing if not a perspective? So there must be something there, some meaning-making element that I haven&apos;t seen or experienced yet, that programming imparts to programmers. I think I probably need to find that if I stick with programming as a discipline, or I&apos;ll burn out. Do a little more reading, see if I can&apos;t pick up on the philosophy underlying it. Try the hat on, so to speak, see if it fits.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>programming</category></item><item><title>What is Rain?</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/what-is-rain/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/what-is-rain/</guid><description>Poetry as a way of thinking.</description><pubDate>Sat, 16 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In college I took a poetry seminar, not because I had any interest in poetry, but because I thought it would be easy. (Not that it&apos;s important, but I was right. There was no homework. We didn&apos;t even have to write poetry.) The professor&apos;s name was &lt;a href=&quot;%5Bhttps://crevice.ro/ryan-tucker-illustrare/%5D(https://crevice.ro/ryan-tucker-illustrare/)&quot;&gt;Ryan Tucker&lt;/a&gt;. He was an adjunct, I think, and couldn&apos;t have been much older than I am now. Often he&apos;d begin class with a video or a song, sometimes to illustrate a point, but also because he apparently thought learning should be fun, a virtue I would appreciate long before I came to recognize it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I liked so much about Ryan was that he taught poetry not as a craft or an art but as a way of thinking. He&apos;d ask us questions like, &lt;em&gt;What is a car?&lt;/em&gt; And we&apos;d answer something like, &lt;em&gt;A car is a vehicle.&lt;/em&gt; And he&apos;d say, &lt;em&gt;Yes, but what else is a car?&lt;/em&gt; And we&apos;d say, &lt;em&gt;A car is a mode of transportation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, but what else is a car?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A car is an expensive necessity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, but what else?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eventually we&apos;d give up. Then Ryan would come out with something like, &lt;em&gt;A car is a chair with four wheels.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ahhh.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was like he was a magician, and had just performed the most wonderful trick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;d go home and come back the next week hungry for more. We&apos;d listen to Ryan&apos;s song, or watch his video, and await the question. And then it would come: &lt;em&gt;What is rain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every object, every concept, comprises layers of somethingness. A car is a mode of transportation, but it is also an expensive necessity, but it is also a chair strapped to four wheels and an engine. Ryan was teaching us to peel back the layers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I&apos;m thinking about something, I&apos;m really trying to answer the question, &lt;em&gt;What is rain?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rain is water that falls from the sky.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yes, but what else?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Qs &amp;amp; As&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; What is a circle?
&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; A circle is every point that is equally far from another point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; What is writing?
&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; Writing is thinking on paper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Q:&lt;/strong&gt; What is a person?
&lt;strong&gt;A:&lt;/strong&gt; A person is a story that tells itself.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category><category>writing</category></item><item><title>Mining and Refining: The Two Modes of Writing</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/mining-and-refining/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/mining-and-refining/</guid><description>You&apos;re either digging for coal, or pressing it into diamonds.</description><pubDate>Thu, 07 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;There are two modes of writing: mining and refining. You&apos;re either digging for coal, or pressing it into diamonds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you mine, you search for raw material. That might look like brainstorming, it might look like research, it might look like eavesdropping. It might look like nothing. You&apos;re watching a movie and it sparks a notion, you write it down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last example is a little different from the others. It feels passive. You weren&apos;t looking for the idea; it came to you. But you had to notice the idea, and you had to write it down, and that requires diligence. So mining is never passive. Just sometimes it runs in the background.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you refine, you take your raw material and shape it into a story, an essay, an article, etc. In film editing, you collect hours of footage, then stitch them together in the cutting room. The writing process is the same. You collect reams of notes, ideas, and disparate scenes, then piece them together in the word processor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Refining might look like reordering chapters or scenes, it might look like reordering beats or rewriting a sentence. The process is the same at every level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you write, you switch between modes. You mine some ideas, start in on refining them. As you do that, your brain&apos;s still mining, so more ideas come to you, and you catch them as they fall. That&apos;s spontaneity, and writing is spontaneity codified.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>writing</category></item><item><title>The Gift God Left</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-gift-god-left/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-gift-god-left/</guid><description>It&apos;s up to us.</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;And now&lt;br /&gt;
taken by the urge&lt;br /&gt;
I will create.&lt;br /&gt;
I will create ruthlessly.&lt;br /&gt;
I will call forth from the depths of imagination&lt;br /&gt;
a world&lt;br /&gt;
and creatures big and small to populate it.&lt;br /&gt;
I will force the breath of life&lt;br /&gt;
down the throats of peaceful sleepers&lt;br /&gt;
who did not ask to be woken.&lt;br /&gt;
Their heads will turn at my Word.&lt;br /&gt;
Their mouths will open at my behest&lt;br /&gt;
and they will proclaim my supremacy.&lt;br /&gt;
They will call me Lord and King and Creator&lt;br /&gt;
and spread their arms like wings&lt;br /&gt;
and try&lt;br /&gt;
and fail&lt;br /&gt;
to embrace the totality of me.&lt;br /&gt;
In their futility&lt;br /&gt;
they will prostrate themselves before me&lt;br /&gt;
and weep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will love my creations&lt;br /&gt;
my people.&lt;br /&gt;
When they are obedient&lt;br /&gt;
I will grant them Good Fortune&lt;br /&gt;
and make miracles happen.&lt;br /&gt;
When they are starving&lt;br /&gt;
I will make manna rain from the sky.&lt;br /&gt;
When they are thirsty&lt;br /&gt;
I will make water spring from solid rock.&lt;br /&gt;
Some of them will see my works and rejoice.&lt;br /&gt;
Some of them will ask&lt;br /&gt;
Why did you allow us to starve in the first place?&lt;br /&gt;
Why did you allow us to thirst?&lt;br /&gt;
They will be right to ask&lt;br /&gt;
and I will punish them accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will love and hate my creations&lt;br /&gt;
as they will hate and love me.&lt;br /&gt;
I will make them good&lt;br /&gt;
and then tempt them to evil.&lt;br /&gt;
When they fall for temptation&lt;br /&gt;
I will take punitive measures against them.&lt;br /&gt;
I will expect more from them than they can give.&lt;br /&gt;
I will not forgive them for being imperfect.&lt;br /&gt;
When they err&lt;br /&gt;
I will beat them down with thunder and famine.&lt;br /&gt;
The earth will open beneath their feet&lt;br /&gt;
the waves will savage their seawalls&lt;br /&gt;
the tempest will rage against the levees of their souls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some spirits will be broken.&lt;br /&gt;
In their brokenness&lt;br /&gt;
though it will be of little comfort to them&lt;br /&gt;
they will serve a noble purpose:&lt;br /&gt;
to convey one Truth of life.&lt;br /&gt;
Other spirits&lt;br /&gt;
rain-battered and seared by rage&lt;br /&gt;
will harden into a bulwark against my love.&lt;br /&gt;
Their resolve will calcify as hate.&lt;br /&gt;
Many of these will claim that they no longer believe in me&lt;br /&gt;
and to that I will say&lt;br /&gt;
Who is it then that you are hating?&lt;br /&gt;
In their confoundment and loathing&lt;br /&gt;
they will reveal another Truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the face of the devastation I send against them&lt;br /&gt;
my people will come to depend on one another.&lt;br /&gt;
They will shake hands&lt;br /&gt;
and help each other to their feet.&lt;br /&gt;
A man will brush the dirt from his neighbor’s shoulder.&lt;br /&gt;
A woman will tend to her neighbor’s wounds.&lt;br /&gt;
A child will offer his friend the last slice of cake&lt;br /&gt;
and he will do so not because he thinks he has to&lt;br /&gt;
but because he understands&lt;br /&gt;
without understanding&lt;br /&gt;
that kindness is just the way we do things around here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just when it looks like my creations&lt;br /&gt;
might be figuring some things out&lt;br /&gt;
I will abandon them.&lt;br /&gt;
I will not mean to.&lt;br /&gt;
It will just happen.&lt;br /&gt;
I will have other things to do&lt;br /&gt;
other people and worlds to create.&lt;br /&gt;
I will leave&lt;br /&gt;
though I will not have gone anywhere.&lt;br /&gt;
I will be here&lt;br /&gt;
where I have always been:&lt;br /&gt;
inside my head.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Though they will look for me&lt;br /&gt;
my creations will not be able to see me.&lt;br /&gt;
They will call my name in the darkness.&lt;br /&gt;
Some will do it loudly&lt;br /&gt;
others from the deep&lt;br /&gt;
desperate quietness of their hearts.&lt;br /&gt;
I will answer none&lt;br /&gt;
if I hear them at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I am not heartless.&lt;br /&gt;
Before I go&lt;br /&gt;
I will leave my people with a gift:&lt;br /&gt;
the hope that I will return.&lt;br /&gt;
It will sustain them for many seasons&lt;br /&gt;
my gift&lt;br /&gt;
but in time&lt;br /&gt;
hope too will fade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then it will be up to them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>The First</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-first/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-first/</guid><description>A different theory of strings.</description><pubDate>Tue, 27 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the beginning&lt;br /&gt;
it wasn’t&lt;br /&gt;
and then it was&lt;br /&gt;
and it has been ever since.&lt;br /&gt;
It is&lt;br /&gt;
was&lt;br /&gt;
and will be&lt;br /&gt;
the First.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The First knows some things.&lt;br /&gt;
It knows&lt;br /&gt;
for instance&lt;br /&gt;
that there is no here or there.&lt;br /&gt;
Rather&lt;br /&gt;
the nature of there is to not be here.&lt;br /&gt;
And there&lt;br /&gt;
here is there&lt;br /&gt;
and there is here.&lt;br /&gt;
The First also knows&lt;br /&gt;
that there is no such thing as chance.&lt;br /&gt;
All things that could be&lt;br /&gt;
are.&lt;br /&gt;
It knows that a question is its own answer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The First floats where there are no streams.&lt;br /&gt;
It is ushered along by currents of a different kind&lt;br /&gt;
with which it does not have the will&lt;br /&gt;
nor the wherewithal&lt;br /&gt;
nor the desire to contend.&lt;br /&gt;
Here&lt;br /&gt;
direction exists all at once&lt;br /&gt;
its countless facets having yet to diverge.&lt;br /&gt;
This is the place between places&lt;br /&gt;
between cause and effect&lt;br /&gt;
between a moment&lt;br /&gt;
and the moment before a moment&lt;br /&gt;
where potential rides the endless ripples of inertia forever&lt;br /&gt;
until it is reached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As it drifts&lt;br /&gt;
the First grasps errant cords of spacetime and pulls them taut.&lt;br /&gt;
One strand at a time&lt;br /&gt;
the fabric of reality tightens into structure.&lt;br /&gt;
The First grips these strings the way a child grips those of a balloon&lt;br /&gt;
and no less than the child does the First want them to slip away.&lt;br /&gt;
So it opens a space in itself and draws the strings across it.&lt;br /&gt;
With a needle found in a dream&lt;br /&gt;
the First sews the ends of the strings to the edges of the opening.&lt;br /&gt;
Then the First plucks the strings&lt;br /&gt;
and one shiver&lt;br /&gt;
one ripple&lt;br /&gt;
one falling domino at a time&lt;br /&gt;
reality creates itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The First does not know where the strings it holds end.&lt;br /&gt;
It cannot follow them&lt;br /&gt;
or they would go slack&lt;br /&gt;
and things would fall apart.&lt;br /&gt;
You may assume&lt;br /&gt;
and reasonably so&lt;br /&gt;
that the First is at&lt;br /&gt;
or is itself&lt;br /&gt;
the center of the universe.&lt;br /&gt;
You would be right&lt;br /&gt;
in a way.&lt;br /&gt;
Everywhere in the universe is the center of the universe.&lt;br /&gt;
Everywhere in the universe is a knot of strings being plucked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you listen carefully&lt;br /&gt;
you can feel the very same vibrations in the molecules that comprise your kitchen table&lt;br /&gt;
or the glass of water that sits on it;&lt;br /&gt;
going forth&lt;br /&gt;
going back&lt;br /&gt;
going up&lt;br /&gt;
coming down.&lt;br /&gt;
If you close your eyes in the quiet dark&lt;br /&gt;
you will feel them inside yourself;&lt;br /&gt;
in the buzzing between your ears&lt;br /&gt;
and in the sort-of hum that tells you where your legs are even when you aren’t moving them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are the undulations of life.&lt;br /&gt;
As you listen&lt;br /&gt;
you will realize you are not so unlike them.&lt;br /&gt;
You push forth and are pulled back&lt;br /&gt;
you climb up and you fall down&lt;br /&gt;
over and over again&lt;br /&gt;
for your entire life&lt;br /&gt;
until you return to the earth&lt;br /&gt;
which&lt;br /&gt;
of course&lt;br /&gt;
you never really left.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This poem originally appeared as a short story in &lt;a href=&quot;https://thecollidescope.com/2022/10/16/the-first/&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Collidescope&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Tales and Canards</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/tales-and-canards/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/tales-and-canards/</guid><description>Rumors.</description><pubDate>Tue, 20 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Some reproving tongues wag&lt;br /&gt;
sanctimonious&lt;br /&gt;
about tales and canards&lt;br /&gt;
only to return to their parlors&lt;br /&gt;
and bedrooms&lt;br /&gt;
and other shrouded places&lt;br /&gt;
and lap up the scuttlebutt&lt;br /&gt;
like so much sweet ambrosia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&apos;t write poetry much, but I do enjoy cadence, and if I ever did become a poet, that would be why. This poem came out of a horror novel I started last year. I abandoned the novel but kept the poem. I thought it captured some of the spookiness I was going for in the original story.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Nothing Rhymes with Kerouac</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/nothing-rhymes-with-kerouac/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/nothing-rhymes-with-kerouac/</guid><description>Not the dumbest thing I&apos;ve ever done.</description><pubDate>Tue, 13 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Jack&lt;br /&gt;
stack&lt;br /&gt;
hack&lt;br /&gt;
rack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mack&lt;br /&gt;
quack&lt;br /&gt;
crack&lt;br /&gt;
pack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;sack&lt;br /&gt;
knack&lt;br /&gt;
snack&lt;br /&gt;
shack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nothing rhymes with Kerouac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;lack slack&lt;br /&gt;
frack thwack&lt;br /&gt;
clack yak&lt;br /&gt;
Hackensack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;change track&lt;br /&gt;
dental plaque&lt;br /&gt;
best foot forward&lt;br /&gt;
take it back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;backtrack&lt;br /&gt;
catch flack&lt;br /&gt;
Aflac&lt;br /&gt;
thumbtack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Big Mac&lt;br /&gt;
heart attack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nothing rhymes with Kerouac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;unpack repack&lt;br /&gt;
jetpack rickrack&lt;br /&gt;
knapsack haversack&lt;br /&gt;
gunnysack paperback&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cardiac Zodiac&lt;br /&gt;
maniac brainiac&lt;br /&gt;
lilac tarmac&lt;br /&gt;
almanac spore sac?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;six-pack racetrack&lt;br /&gt;
smokestack roof rack&lt;br /&gt;
off the rack Prozac&lt;br /&gt;
ransack stickleback&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;coal black dirt track&lt;br /&gt;
unstack spice rack&lt;br /&gt;
wolf pack Kodiak&lt;br /&gt;
ice pack butt crack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;haystack Kodak&lt;br /&gt;
caddy-shack cul-de-sac&lt;br /&gt;
sad sack setback&lt;br /&gt;
coatrack gimcrack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;fast-track dye pack&lt;br /&gt;
chimney stack Bernie Mac&lt;br /&gt;
Seabiscuit Hardtack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nothing rhymes with Kerouac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;blowback buyback&lt;br /&gt;
bareback pushback&lt;br /&gt;
backpack while back&lt;br /&gt;
out back cut back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;throwback comeback&lt;br /&gt;
drawback feedback&lt;br /&gt;
horseback camelback&lt;br /&gt;
saddleback quarterback&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hold back hark back&lt;br /&gt;
hatchback humpback&lt;br /&gt;
hunchback halfback&lt;br /&gt;
water off a duck&apos;s back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;take aback razorback&lt;br /&gt;
laid back rollback&lt;br /&gt;
callback cash back&lt;br /&gt;
&quot;pickaback means &quot;piggyback&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;switchback turnback&lt;br /&gt;
mossback setback&lt;br /&gt;
finback kickback&lt;br /&gt;
clawback fatback&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;swayback talk back&lt;br /&gt;
tailback fullback&lt;br /&gt;
touchback wingback&lt;br /&gt;
softback tie-back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cornerback canvasback&lt;br /&gt;
huckaback ladder-back&lt;br /&gt;
back-to-back diamondback&lt;br /&gt;
give the kid his money back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;playback payback&lt;br /&gt;
hit back fight back&lt;br /&gt;
right back surprise attack!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nothing rhymes with Kerouac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;click-clack  tic-tac&lt;br /&gt;
yik-yak bric-a-brac&lt;br /&gt;
knick-knack paddy-whack&lt;br /&gt;
give a dog a shot of smack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;book stack bushwhack&lt;br /&gt;
bootjack HVAC&lt;br /&gt;
shop vac toe crack&lt;br /&gt;
goddammit put that back&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;starterpack shoe rack&lt;br /&gt;
Cadillac train track&lt;br /&gt;
on track offtrack&lt;br /&gt;
sidetrack power&apos;s back!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amtrak amnesiac&lt;br /&gt;
somnambulist insomniac&lt;br /&gt;
dipsomaniac ammoniac&lt;br /&gt;
need an aphrodisiac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;plan of attack counterattack&lt;br /&gt;
cyberattack asthma attack&lt;br /&gt;
Pontiac elegiac&lt;br /&gt;
enlist a pyromaniac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;prickleback Radioshack&lt;br /&gt;
bike rack streetcar track&lt;br /&gt;
anorak hackmatack&lt;br /&gt;
out of whack demoniac&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;jet black in the black&lt;br /&gt;
blackjack Jack Black&lt;br /&gt;
flapjack Union Jack&lt;br /&gt;
crackerjack applejack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;steeplejack cheapjack&lt;br /&gt;
skip jack screw Jack!&lt;br /&gt;
phone jack lumberjack&lt;br /&gt;
supplejack amberjack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;natterjack yellow jack&lt;br /&gt;
carjack skyjack&lt;br /&gt;
hijack hi, Jack!&lt;br /&gt;
bye, Jack! jumping jack&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;cognac hit the sack&lt;br /&gt;
cat on crack sulindac&lt;br /&gt;
wisecrack get shellacked&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NOTHING RHYMES WITH KEROUAC&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Notes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wrote this poem when I lived in Marfa, Texas. A friend of a friend was hosting a beat poetry night in honor of what would have been Jack Kerouac&apos;s 100th birthday. When he found out I held a writing degree from the University of Iowa (the undergraduate program, not the Writers&apos; Workshop), he invited me to write something to read at the party.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, I know nothing about poetry or Jack Kerouac. But what the hell, anybody can write nonsense. The resulting poem turned out to be a pretty nice exercise in cadence. Note that it&apos;s meant to be performed, not read, so if there&apos;s no one around (or even if there is), feel free to belt it out.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>poetry</category></item><item><title>Get Out of the Water</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/get-out-of-the-water/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/get-out-of-the-water/</guid><description>On worry, intuition, and trying new things.</description><pubDate>Tue, 06 Feb 2024 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Paul Graham once described &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulgraham.com/love.html&quot;&gt;prestige as a magnet&lt;/a&gt; that warps your ability to tell the difference between what you like and what you&apos;d like to like. I think that&apos;s right, and I think you could extend the analogy to any number of confounding forces (desire, greed, peer pressure, parental pressure, societal pressure, how good you are at lying to yourself, conventional wisdom, overconfidence, underconfidence, misguided devotion to a bygone aspiration, et al) that distort your thinking, cloud your motives, and altogether make understanding yourself and why you do the things you do much harder than understanding yourself and why you do the things you do has any right to be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example: For a long time I wanted to be a screenwriter. That was my first real aspiration, and I pursued it at a steady-ish pace for about nine years. But in all that time, I finished just one screenplay and a handful of short stories. Eventually, I began to wonder if I liked writing at all. It was a question easier asked than answered, because I was attempting to answer it while under the influence of several magnets. There was the Dubious Magnet of Underconfidence, child of the Brittle Magnet of Low Self-Esteem; the Statistically-Backed Magnet of Sunk Costs;  the Misguided Magnet of Devotion to a Bygone Aspiration; and the Supreme Magnet of Not Trusting Myself. Any thinking about whether I liked writing was followed by pondering about whether I was thinking clearly about whether I liked writing, and the pondering in turn was followed by brooding over whether I was pondering clearly about thinking clearly about whether I liked writing. I&apos;d get so turned around that I&apos;d go back to writing simply because it was simpler, and because, frankly, I didn&apos;t have a better idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Magnets are like pythons: the more you struggle, the tighter they squeeze you. The only way to escape is to relax, stop thinking, and let intuition take the wheel. (Disclaimer: This strategy has not been tested on actual pythons.) That&apos;s not to say it&apos;s as simple as closing your eyes and &quot;listening to your gut.&quot; Intuition is a powerful machine, but it&apos;s useless without data. That data comes from experience. I don&apos;t have to wonder if I prefer West Texas summers to Iowa winters. I &lt;em&gt;know&lt;/em&gt; I prefer West Texas summers to Iowa winters because I&apos;ve lived through both. If you&apos;re a fish and you suspect, given all you&apos;ve heard, that you might like living on dry land, no amount of cool-headed theorizing or desperate agonizing will help you, because it&apos;s impossible to tell if you like living on dry land based on what you &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt; living on dry land &lt;em&gt;might&lt;/em&gt; be like. If you want to know if you like living on dry land, you have to get out of the water.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It wasn&apos;t until I started coding that I finally realized how much I didn&apos;t like writing (fiction writing, mind you). I&apos;d been forcing words onto the page for so long that I&apos;d forgotten what it felt like to enjoy something that was also hard. Far from forcing myself to code, I couldn&apos;t &lt;em&gt;stop&lt;/em&gt; myself from coding. I didn&apos;t have to wonder anymore if I liked writing. I &lt;em&gt;knew&lt;/em&gt; I didn&apos;t like writing because I&apos;d found something much more engaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One caveat here is that you won&apos;t have a strong preference for most things. If you, the fish, get out of the water and find that the beach isn&apos;t doing it for you, don&apos;t worry about it, and don&apos;t settle. Instead, go to the forest and see how that feels. If that doesn&apos;t work, try the Arctic. You may find that you don&apos;t have a strong preference for any climate. That&apos;s okay, too. All it means is that your environment isn&apos;t as important to you as you thought it was. That&apos;s good data. Collect it, and carry on. Keep feeding the machine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And don&apos;t worry about wasting time. Worrying about wasting time is a waste of time. Trying things isn&apos;t. When you get out of the water, life becomes more interesting and more fun. You&apos;ll do things you wouldn&apos;t have done otherwise. You&apos;ll go places you wouldn&apos;t have gone, see things you wouldn&apos;t have seen, and meet people you wouldn&apos;t have met, and the next time you find yourself talking to someone you feel the inexplicable need to impress, you&apos;ll have a story to tell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another caveat is that while strong preferences are obvious, they aren&apos;t always obvious immediately. To know if you like something, you have to spend some time with it. When I first started coding, I was too intimidated to like it. I don&apos;t have a mathy brain, and it seemed like the kind of thing that only people with mathy brains were good at. It took two years of dabbling to convince me that coding was something I could do. Only then did I start to like it. That&apos;s the catch-22 here: You don&apos;t want to spend any more time than necessary doing things you don&apos;t like, but you don&apos;t necessarily know if you like or dislike something until you&apos;ve spent a little time with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The best thing you can do is leave yourself alone. Try to relax. Untether yourself, and see where you drift. If you keep drifting back to something, don&apos;t question it. &lt;em&gt;A Serious Man&lt;/em&gt; is one of my favorite movies. The first time I saw it, my reaction was a question mark. The second time I saw it, my reaction was a question mark and a smile. The third time I saw it, I fell in love. I don&apos;t know what soundless voice it was that coaxed me into revisiting the movie, and I don&apos;t care. But it&apos;s still there, and I&apos;m still listening.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Further Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.paulgraham.com/love.html&quot;&gt;How to Do What You Love&lt;/a&gt; by Paul Graham&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.themarginalian.org/2012/02/27/purpose-work-love/&quot;&gt;How to Find Your Purpose and Do What You Love&lt;/a&gt; by Maria Popova&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2018/04/picking-career.html&quot;&gt;How to Pick a Career (That Actually Fits You)&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Urban&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content:encoded><category>life</category><category>work</category></item><item><title>And God Said, &quot;Care, Dammit&quot;</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/care-dammit/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/care-dammit/</guid><description>Talmudic wisdom in &apos;The Exorcist.&apos;</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I was working on a short story about an exorcist (which I&apos;ve since abandoned) so I decided to read &lt;em&gt;The Exorcist.&lt;/em&gt; I&apos;ve seen the movie but can&apos;t say I&apos;m a fan. The book is excellent. One passage stood out. It&apos;s said by Merrin, the senior exorcist, to Damien, the amateur who&apos;s been having a crisis of faith:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Long ago I despaired of ever loving my neighbor. Certain people repelled me. How could I love them? I thought. It tormented me. It led me to despair of myself, and from that,  very soon, to despair of my own God. My faith was shattered. But at last I realized that God would never ask of me that which I know to be psychologically impossible; that the love which He asked was in my&lt;/em&gt; will &lt;em&gt;and not meant to be felt as emotion at all. He was asking that I&lt;/em&gt; act &lt;em&gt;with love; that I&lt;/em&gt; do &lt;em&gt;unto others; and that I should do it unto those who repelled me, I believe, was a greater act of love than any other.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The priests in &lt;em&gt;The Exorcists&lt;/em&gt; are Jesuits, but this passage struck me as Talmudic. In Judaism, you aren&apos;t asked to care. You&apos;re commanded to. And if you can&apos;t bring yourself to care, that does not relieve you of the obligation to act as though you do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In turn, this reminds me of a sentiment I&apos;ve heard expressed by &lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/&quot;&gt;Tim Urban&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.astralcodexten.com/&quot;&gt;Scott Alexander&lt;/a&gt;, among others: You only get to call yourself principled if you apply your principles to people you can&apos;t stand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In other words, kindness counts when it&apos;s easy, but it counts more, maybe much more, when it&apos;s hard.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>books</category></item><item><title>It&apos;s Not the Story&apos;s Fault You Thought You Were Still on the Ranch</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/lonesome-dove/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/lonesome-dove/</guid><description>Two short essays and one longish essay inspired by &apos;Lonesome Dove.&apos;</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; is a story about the lust for adventure, a force so powerful it can rip you from the arms of comfort and chuck you into the jaws of death. Daredevils everywhere will relate to Gus and Woodrow. They are men who can&apos;t stand to sit still. Nobody makes them leave Lonesome Dove. They leave because they&apos;re bored. Thus, their subsequent wounds are self-inflicted. These guys aren&apos;t naive. They&apos;re not young soldiers harboring idealized notions of war. They know blood, and they know battle, and they know terror and they know anguish. They don&apos;t leave Lonesome Dove despite these things; they leave because of them. The danger is the point. Gus and Woodrow risk grief and pain so that when death does inevitably come for them, they can greet it feeling like they&apos;ve lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The vanity of grand romance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you decide you&apos;re in love with someone, when you fixate on somebody in that way, what you&apos;ve inadvertently done is made them a major character in the story you&apos;re writing about yourself. And what you&apos;ve also done is decided, subconsciously, that the only way your story can have a happy ending is if you and the object of your affection get together at the end of it. You&apos;ve seen this attitude toward love affirmed a thousand times in romances, romantic comedies, and romantic epics. What &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; does is less common. The series takes that grand romantic arc that is so familiar and reveals a side of it--or an iteration of it--that is delusional, conceited, and vainglorious. Which is to say, sometimes you cross a thousand miles of prairie in order to reunite with the love of your life only to find that they&apos;re writing a story of their own, and you&apos;re not in it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;It&apos;s not the story&apos;s fault you thought you were still on the ranch&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/why-happiness-is-overrated&quot;&gt;Mark Manson&lt;/a&gt; defines emotion, and I&apos;m paraphrasing here, as the product of a misalignment between our expectations and reality. We expect one thing to happen, but then something else happens, and we feel a way about it. That way might be good or bad. When life is better than we expect, we might experience happiness. When life is worse than we expect, we might experience sadness. And depending on the extent to which our expectations are violated, we might feel those emotions to a greater or lesser degree. When life isn&apos;t just better but &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; better than we expect, maybe we experience not just happiness but &lt;em&gt;elation.&lt;/em&gt; Likewise, when life isn&apos;t just worse but &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; worse than we expect, maybe we experience not just sadness but &lt;em&gt;devastation.&lt;/em&gt; If we follow that train of thought, we can come up with a working definition of the emotion we&apos;re here to talk about, which is shock. In the same way that we might define devastation as &quot;sadness, but more so,&quot; we might define shock as &quot;surprise, but more so.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s imagine for a moment that you&apos;re browsing the shelves in a video rental store (let&apos;s also imagine for a moment that video rental stores still exist) and you come across a copy of &lt;em&gt;Avengers: Endgame.&lt;/em&gt; Only this copy of &lt;em&gt;Endgame&lt;/em&gt; doesn&apos;t look quite right. The costumes look a little off, some of the actors are different, and the description on the back doesn&apos;t match the movie you remember. And since you can pretty readily tell that it&apos;s not a porno, you rightly conclude that it&apos;s a version of &lt;em&gt;Endgame&lt;/em&gt; from an alternate universe. Naturally you&apos;re curious, so you take it home and pop it in your VCR player and you sit down to watch. And for the first few scenes the movie feels pretty much like you&apos;d expect. Again, some of the actors and costumes are different, but the production value is there, it&apos;s no knockoff, and by and large it feels like a Marvel movie should feel. It&apos;s light, it&apos;s fun, it&apos;s melodramatic. There&apos;s danger, but that danger is accompanied by, in the back of your mind, an essential understanding that everything&apos;s going to turn out okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then comes a scene where Captain America has to face down one of Thanos&apos;s henchman. They&apos;re going head-to-head, and for a while it seems like a pretty even match, and you&apos;re not sure if Captain America&apos;s going to win but you&apos;re pretty sure (again, because of that essential understanding) that he&apos;s at least going to come out of this relatively unscathed. But then something happens that you don&apos;t expect. The henchman pulls a knife from his boot and plunges it into Captain America&apos;s stomach. He twists the blade and wrenches it upward, then yanks it out and Captain America&apos;s guts spill all over the floor. Cap falls to his knees, screaming in agony. Tears spill down his face as he tries in vain to stuff his own entrails back into his body. He screams for an agonizingly long time, perhaps minutes, until finally the henchman steps forward and finishes the job, and that&apos;s the end of Captain America.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How would you react to that? Everybody&apos;s different, so maybe some of you would be horrified, maybe some of you would find it comical, but I imagine that everybody, to one degree or another, would be pretty taken aback. And the reason you&apos;d be taken aback is that you weren&apos;t expecting that kind of behavior from a Marvel movie. If you were watching a different movie or show, say, &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt;, it&apos;d be a different story. The scene would still be upsetting, but you wouldn&apos;t be taken aback. Because you &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; expect that kind of behavior from &lt;em&gt;Game of Thrones.&lt;/em&gt; That&apos;s that world. But it&apos;s not Marvel. So by disemboweling Captain America, the alternate version of &lt;em&gt;Endgame&lt;/em&gt; shattered your understanding of the world you thought you were in. That&apos;s how stories shock you: by introducing you to a world that seems to be governed by certain rules, and then doing something that seems to violate those rules.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, the tricky thing about shock is that if you&apos;re already expecting a certain kind of behavior from a story, then the story can&apos;t shock you with it. But if you aren&apos;t expecting such behavior, and then the story behaves that way, you&apos;ll feel like you&apos;ve been cheated. You&apos;ll feel like you&apos;ve been lied to. So how does a story strike that balance? By laying the groundwork. If a story that shocks you is doing its job right, the shocking thing that it does doesn&apos;t &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; violate its established rules. If a story is doing its job right, it&apos;s been telling you exactly what it is the whole time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris Cooper in &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; plays July Johnson, a goodhearted but somewhat irresolute sheriff who&apos;s strong-armed by a woman into tracking down her husband&apos;s killer. And July&apos;s wife (played by Glenne Headly) makes him take their young son Bryan along so she can run off back to the guy she really wants to be married to. That feels a bit convoluted but it&apos;s not important. What&apos;s important is that July takes his kid into the wilderness to track down a murderer, and unfortunately for them, their path crosses with that of Blue Duck, a vicious bandit and the villain of the series. I don&apos;t recall the exact scenario, I think July and Bryan find some of Blue Duck&apos;s victims or something, but anyway July tells Bryan to stay back while he goes down the hill to check for survivors. And so he goes down the hill, and while he&apos;s down there Blue Duck emerges from the bushes and kills Bryan. He kills the little boy. With a knife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was shocked. And more than shocked, I was upset. I was upset because I felt betrayed. And I felt betrayed because I didn&apos;t think this was a world where kids got murdered. I felt like the story had cheated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whenever I feel this way about a story, there are generally two possibilities: Either the story fucked up, or I did. &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; is a miniseries based on a Pulitzer Prize-winning novel. I&apos;m a person who is somewhat less accomplished than that. It seemed prudent to give the series the benefit of the doubt. Anyway I liked the show, I knew it was something of quality, so I sat down to figure out if maybe I&apos;d missed something. It didn&apos;t take long to realize that the story hadn&apos;t cheated me at all. I just hadn&apos;t been paying attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the brilliance of &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; lies in the subtlety with which it introduces violence. We begin the story, as I said before, in the arms of comfort. Lonesome Dove is a peaceful place. A bit boring maybe, and a little sad, but it&apos;s home. It&apos;s a safe place. But then we leave home, and it isn&apos;t long before danger rears its head. At first it&apos;s a fun kind of danger. It&apos;s stealing horses from rancher-tyrants and it&apos;s watching Glenne Headly watch men murder each other over her. It might not always be pleasant, especially that last example, but it&apos;s the kind of danger and violence that fits with the world we&apos;ve been introduced to. It&apos;s the kind of thing we expect, so much so that we&apos;d actually be disappointed if it wasn&apos;t there. And then, at end of the first episode, &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; delivers its first real blow. Sean, an Irish immigrant who falls in with the heroes early on, has the misfortune to walk his horse through a river infested by water moccasins (that&apos;s another name for cottonmouth snakes). It&apos;s a shocking scene in itself, but it&apos;s still fair play. It&apos;s the most horrific scene we&apos;ve witnessed, but it&apos;s not so far outside the scope of what we&apos;ve come to expect that we feel cheated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see what the show&apos;s doing. Each act of violence is grislier than the last. In one scene Gus comes under fire from Blue Duck&apos;s men on an open plain and stabs his own horse to death so he can use it as cover. In another, an enslaved woman named Janey breaks the knees of her captor with a frying pan. By the end of the second episode, when Blue Duck kills Bryan, we&apos;re well within the type of world where kids get stabbed to death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet, Bryan&apos;s death shocked me. And yet, I felt betrayed. And yet, if I felt that way, it was only because I&apos;d become complacent. I&apos;d unwittingly failed to take &lt;em&gt;Lonesome Dove&lt;/em&gt; seriously, even though it had never once hidden its face from me, but revealed itself at a measured pace. It did its job, and it did it well. It&apos;s not the story&apos;s fault I thought we were still on the ranch.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>movies</category><category>tv</category></item><item><title>Buffalo Sorting and My First Gambling Foray</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/buffalo-sorting/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/buffalo-sorting/</guid><description>Notes from the Badlands.</description><pubDate>Sun, 12 Nov 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Early October I went to South Dakota for the first time since I was a kid. I have a friend from college whose parents own a cabin in the Black Hills which she and her boyfriend (also a college friend) go to a few times a year, and I’d been talking about going with them for some time. I landed in Sioux Falls. My friends were driving from Des Moines, so it worked out that they could pick me up from the airport and we set out from there.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our first stop was the Badlands. The park was impressive but not nearly as entertaining as the gas station we stopped at beforehand, which abutted a colony of highly extroverted and rather rotund prairie dogs. Rotund because well-fed, well-fed because what you do at this gas station is you go in and buy a bag of peanuts (preferably salted) and take them out and stand among the prairie dog mounds and wait for the inhabitants to emerge. When they do, you toss a handful of nuts and watch the chunky suckers scramble. They aren’t shy, these prairie dogs. I was on the verge of feeding one by hand when my friend happened to mention that prairie dogs carry the Black Plague, and I decided to stand down. I&apos;m pleased to say I feel fine. So far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We stayed in Wall overnight and the next day drove on through to the Black Hills. My friend’s parents have an ATV, so the first day we took it up into the mountains on some truly hairy back roads near the Wyoming border, the upshot of which (if you survive the trip) is you get to a lookout where you have a 360-degree view of the Black hills in one direction and Wyoming in the other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That little trek turned out to be the highlight of the trip, but what I was most looking forward to going into the week was Deadwood. You may know that Deadwood was a gold rush town back in the day, and more recently the subject of a well-regarded HBO series of the same name, which I&apos;m rather fond of. Sadly, I was disappointed. Nearly every building in Deadwood that isn’t a shop is a casino, which I hadn’t remembered from my last visit. The upside to that was I&apos;d never gambled before, and being in Rome (as it were), I decided it was as good a time and a good a place as any to check that item off the old bucket list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We played slots. (There are few tables games in Deadwood, but I wasn’t interested in those anyway). I picked one of the older ones because I have an analog sensibility and it contained actual spinning gizmos instead of a screen, and it was probably for that reason that the machine seemed to have an almost halcyon glow about it—something alluring, something almost…trustworthy. Still, my faith in that sort of thing only goes so far. I decided I wasn&apos;t willing to lose more than twenty dollars, so a twenty&apos;s what I put in. I bet in two-dollar increments and I&apos;ll be damned if I didn&apos;t win eight-five dollars on my second or third spin. Score one for hunches.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I don’t know much about gambling, but I do know that quit while you’re ahead are the words to live by when it comes to such affairs, and I&apos;m proud to say I heeded them then. I wasn’t about to count on that machine being so generous a second time, so I hit the CASH OUT button and promptly went to another. I chose one on the far side of the room. My theory was that the farther away the new machine was, the less likely it was to have heard me win on the other one. Lo and behold, the new machine turned my eighty-five dollars into one hundred and twenty-eight. Again, this up from an initial twenty. Now we were in business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did seriously consider quitting at this point. I considered that it would be completely stupid to do so, given that I&apos;d just made a hundred and eight dollars in about fifteen minutes, and since we had the whole day ahead of us, that meant I could easily have over twelve hundred dollars in my pocket by suppertime.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can probably guess what happened next. My working theory was that if I’d picked two winners right off the bat the chances were good that I’d find another before too long. Well, that logic didn’t pan out. I wandered all over that casino and didn’t find a single machine that was as good to me as those first two had been. By the time we’d finished, I had forty-four dollars on my voucher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, I’d started with twenty dollars if you recall, meaning I won twenty-four. For the investment strategists among you, that amounts to a 120% gain. Not bad by Wall Street standards. Still, my gain had I stopped at one hundred and twenty-eight dollars would have been 540%. Had I taken the time to do that math at the outset, I may have convinced myself to quit then and there and dinner would have been on me. As it was, we split the bill three ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of the trip was exactly as relaxing and uneventful as it should have been. I&apos;ll close with one more brief anecdote.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the second to last day we went to Custer State Park with the idea of seeing some buffalo and driving up Needles Highway. What we didn&apos;t know was that that was also the day the buffalo were being sorted, which is evidently a thing they do at Custer State Park. Every September the park rangers, accompanied by a number of volunteers, round up the herd so select specimens can be sold to various ranches and meat sellers. I didn&apos;t know any of this, but it dawned on me after the fact that the bison burger I&apos;d had in Wall must have come from somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>travel</category></item><item><title>Riddled with Words: &apos;The Maltese Falcon&apos;</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/maltese-falcon/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/maltese-falcon/</guid><description>Every bastard gets what&apos;s coming to them.</description><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Sam Spade exhibits a degree of unhinged lunacy on par with Hamlet, and there’s something to that, isn’t there, because you know what they have in common? They’re both damaged goods. Hamlet’s uncle killed his father and then had shameless carnal relations with his mother. It’s enough to drive anyone to San Francisco, and Sam, well we don’t know what he’s been through but part of the art of filmmaking as John Huston so deftly demonstrates is knowing what to say and when to say it, yes, but also knowing what not to say. No, it wouldn’t do if we knew too much about Sam Spade, if we knew what abuses he’s endured. If we knew that we’d pity him, and worse, he wouldn’t be so damn cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam is pretty slick. He calls you sweetheart and gets away with it. He likes being the smartest guy in the room, it’s a hobby he turned into a career. He’s emotionally detached to a pathological degree (never does he express anything like grief over the death of his partner, except perhaps in the anger he directs at O’Shaughnessy while accusing her of being Archer’s killer), though he has appetites, like any other man, which isn’t to say he can’t love, because he can, it’s just he knows love is bad for business, and in his business, what’s bad for business gets you killed. More than that he knows love’s not to be trusted, having made himself an expert on such matters by sleeping with his partner’s wife. Sam’s no gambler but he can recognize a hand and knows when to hedge his bets. So if it comes down to you or him, sweetheart, it’s you all the way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All the facts are on one side. Now, on the other side we’ve got what? All we’ve got is that maybe you love me and maybe I love you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam’s affair with Mrs. Archer is revealed early in the story, just after Mr. Archer’s murder, a smart move by Huston as Sam’s infidelity is key to his psychology. It goes like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam knows there are bad people in the world, not just because he deals with them on a daily basis but because he is one. He understands this about himself even if he doesn’t care. Or maybe that’s selling him short. Maybe he does care but thinks he’s a lost cause, and maybe he’s right. Moreover, he may very well consider habitual depravity essential to his line of work. The people he encounters, clients and adversaries alike, the dreck washed up on his threshold by the feculent tides of desperation, envy, greed, and other sins are the kinds of people to whom sentiment is as blood in the water to a shark. It’s not if you can’t beat em join em, it’s if you want to beat em you better join em. Get soft and you’ll wind up a soft virgin corpse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Still, Sam never sinks to the level of O’Shaughnessy or Gutman. He’s not a thief or a murderer. But he sinks just low enough to get a clear picture of the bottom, and there he floats, below him the pit, above him the crushing weight of penance. Maybe that’s why Spade likes being a private dick, because it puts him in contact with these scum-of-the-earth types who by juxtaposition make him look like a little angel. A bit petty, sure, but Sam has that side to him. Look at his face as he watches the fat man go to pieces along with the lead facade of the fake falcon. There’s something predatory in that Cheshire cat grin, coupled with disdain and no small measure of grim satisfaction. Nothing in the world brings him so much pleasure as watching Gutman despair as his grand designs for which he has been willing to sacrifice his analogous son fail to bear fruit. Spade delights in his comeuppance, drinking in the schadenfreude like lifeblood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is until it’s O’Shaughnessy’s turn to get hers. For that scene Sam’s grin disappears, replaced by his default hard-boiled stoicism that only just veils his desperate resignation. He knows O’Shaughnessy has to take the fall, all that’s left is to talk himself into it. She says she loves him but she’s never played square with him for half an hour at a stretch and anyway what if somebody finds out he not only let his partner’s killer get away clean but took her to bed? How can he be sure if he covers for her she won’t turn around and put the proverbial knife in his back? It’s the facts on one side and love on the other. One of those you can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cairo: You always have a very smooth explanation ready.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Spade: What do you want me to do, learn to stutter?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sam Spade is an action hero who riddles the bad guys not with bullets but with words. He hails down verbiage like a martial arts expert hails down blows. He’s the Jackie Chan of elocution. With words he dodges and deflects, charm and  seduces, feints and strikes with machine-gun &lt;em&gt;rat-a-tat-tat&lt;/em&gt; rhetoric, firing so fast his opponents hardly have time to put up their defenses and some of them come apart at the seams, like young Wilmer at whose armor of confidence and stoic machismo Spade chips away until it shatters altogether and Wilmer is reduced to an angry, tearful, fatherless boy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the same, Spade meets his match in Gutman, the fat man. The thing about the fat man is he’s fat, and nothing’s getting through that. He’s too old to be teased to shambles. He’s amused by Spade’s antics more than cowed, and the fact is that right up to the finish it’s in no way clear that Sam’s going to win this one. Matter of fact everything seems to be going just swimmingly for Gutman right up until he unwraps the counterfeit avian statuette, and that’s no clever switcharoo by Sam either. The falcon is made lead only by an act of cinematic providence. Why? Probably because the alternative would have been pretty boring. Moreover it lets Sam, and by extension us, relish the look of bewildered despair that graces Gutman’s flabby jowls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For his part, Sam doesn’t seem the least bit surprised. Could it be that under everything he is, in his way, a man of faith? Not that he’d call it that. Sam has no use for faith. He believes what he knows, and what he knows is this: sooner or later, every bastard gets what’s coming to them, himself included.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>movies</category></item><item><title>Cinderella in Reverse: &apos;Roman Holiday&apos;</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/cinderella-in-reverse/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/cinderella-in-reverse/</guid><description>Instead of putting the glass slipper on, Ann kicks it off.</description><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it’s her eyes, or how her expression always bespeaks the shadow of a smile, even when she’s crying, but we warm to Princess Ann straightaway. Of course it helps that she’s young and Audrey Hepburn, but really it has to do with the way we meet her; in the midst of a lengthy and exhausting royal public relations tour of Europe. By the time she finally finishes shaking the hands of an endless entourage of aristocrats and (one presumes) eligible bachelors, she has us completely. Her humanity is subsequently cemented via her disarming mishap with a shoe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there’s something about that shoe. It’s Cinderella in reverse: Rather than putting the glass slipper on, Ann kicks it off (the rest of her royal trappings will soon follow) the first symbolic step in her semiotic transformation from princess to just a regular old girl. It’s not that the royal shoe doesn’t fit. It’s just that it’s terribly uncomfortable, especially after such a long day and so much standing, and really, given the option, she in all likelihood wouldn’t wear it at all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film is aware of the analogy; the princess herself references the fairy tale at least once. This to say that Roman Holiday isn’t afraid to be about what it’s about; what in the parlance of our times we call “on the nose,” an approach that these days is more likely to elicit an eye-roll than a teardrop, if only because such blatant sentimentality is so ill-suited to modern dramatic conventions and linguistic aesthetics. Roman Holiday remade tomorrow, aspiring to arrive at the same narrative destination as its progenitor, would have to come to it via a more more circuitous, subtextual route. But in 1953, the film’s unabashed earnestness — embodied in its characters, who if simplistic are only the more lovable for it — far from being a weakness, is its greatest strength. When Joe tells Ann, “Life isn’t always what one likes,” it’s the unfiltered, unveiled, inescapable truth of it that drives the stake through our hearts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Roman Holiday isn’t perfect. There’s more than enough narrative wheel-spinning to go around, even if that wheel-spinning is uproarious. Some punching up, a little tightening of the narrative screws, a little conscientious aligning of the narrative stars would have gone a long way. Then again. A plot would be decidedly ill-suited to a movie whose lead character hates schedules, as would manufactured melodrama. (After all, we never really believe that Joe’s going to write that story, do we?) Spontaneity is the name of the game. Examined from this angle, a subtle brilliance begins to reveal itself. We know from the beginning that Ann will, sooner or later, whether she likes it or not, return to the embassy; the frame of the picture is enshrined in its premise, and puts to us a question, which serves as the engine of the story: how much living can one do in one day? There’s your tension. There’s your ticking clock. It’s not will they/won’t they. This is Ann’s movie. Like a toy mouse, the film winds her up, then lets her go wherever she wants, contrivance be damned, and Roman Holiday becomes to our eyes — like innocence, like youth — an ethereal adventure, too perfect to last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By the end, Ann has grown up a bit. She has had her day in the sun. It is midnight. The carriage has again become a pumpkin. Time to go home. She returns to the throne with quiet grace, not having escaped the gilded cage, but better equipped to bear its burdens. The child in Ann dies so the princess can live. It is death by obligation. Put less dramatically, her yearning for freedom isn’t gone, but now she has a place to keep it: her memories, rendered in photographs, themselves contained in an envelope, to be procured when she needs them, but otherwise tucked away, hidden.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joe, for his part, lingers in the grand hall — perhaps hoping that he is in one of those romantic movies where the girl comes running back, dress blowing in the wind, heralded by a triumphant brass-filled score — waiting for a happy ending that we know isn’t coming. He knows it too.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>movies</category></item><item><title>Absence of Meaning in &apos;The Lighthouse&apos;</title><link>https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-lighthouse/</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://samfeldstein.xyz/blog/the-lighthouse/</guid><description>A successful exercise in atmosphere, but it&apos;s probably about nothing.</description><pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;All movies have to become real, on some level, in order to do their good work, and some of them can only achieve this by taking active steps to distance themselves from reality. All movies do this to some extent simply by appearing on a screen, but some of them, as with &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt;, need a little more than that. Eggers’s choice to shoot on 35mm negative in an aspect ratio of 1.19:1 is the kind of cinematic idiosyncrasy usually referred to as an “artistic” decision, though its effect here is intensely pragmatic. Watching something so outwardly anachronistic forces a peculiar kind of dissonance. It untethers us from the real world, such as we experience it, and with the blast of a foghorn, tips us headlong into the film’s frigid, perpetually overcast, horrific, salt-sprayed world. And now that we’re here, we’ll buy whatever bizarro bunkum the film wants to sell. Throw in all the shrieking banshee mermaids and tentacle monsters you want, we’ll eat it up and ask for seconds. In the words of Sam Spade, we’ll take it and we’ll like it. All this to say that &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; isn’t so much a movie as it is an experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It follows that a movie in which the existence of a higher power is as explicit as anything would itself be ineffable. Such is the nature of divinity (benevolent or otherwise), embodied in this case by the mysterious and ethereal light, coveted by Howard (Robert Pattinson) and jealously guarded by Wake (Willem Dafoe). More than being deliberately designed to thwart any kind of conclusive analysis, &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; seems to revel in its own ambiguity as it hails down a practically belligerent barrage of folkloric, mythical, and biblical imagery. So many symbols and references are crammed in–though, impressively, never in a way that feels forced or contrived–that it nearly amounts to an assault on the associative imagination. At times, it almost feels like the movie is daring you to understand it–daring you, because if you can make sense of its dream-logic, you just might be crazy. In the wake of such ambiguity, the scope of possible interpretation is broadened such that any number of thematic assertions (isolation, guilt and salvation, identity, divinity, sexuality, social and professional hierarchies, etc.) may be made and subsequently justified by any number of in-text corollaries (the island setting, Howard’s confession, Howard and Wake sharing the same forename, the light itself, the sexual tension between Howard and Wake, the power dynamic between Howard and Wake, etc.). The presence of so many plausibilities belies any attempt to settle on a singular summation (not that that’s going to stop us from trying), and allows each viewer to cleave to whichever motif they connect most strongly with. This effectively broadens &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse’s&lt;/em&gt; appeal and might explain how a film this enigmatic grossed eighteen million dollars at the box office.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The central enigmatic figure in the film is, naturally, the light. Insofar as it has one, parsing the light’s personality amounts to not much more than guesswork. It’s surely enrapturing, given the way Wake worships it and Howard desires it, and it exudes an aura of angelic purity. It looms over the island from the tip of its ivory tower, looking down sternly on its (mostly) willing servants. There’s a sense that it’s assessing their worth–or at least Howard’s; Wake may already have proven himself–keeping tally of their transgressions, ready to wreak havoc on them at the slightest sign of dissent. But of the strange phenomena that befall Howard (the abrasive seabird, the mermaid, the change in the wind, etc.), it is unclear which, if any, the light causes. It may be that there is some other ineffable consciousness (Neptune, perhaps?) at work here. Howard’s killing of the seabird, followed directly by a Mary Poppins-style pan to the weathervane, which does a complete one-eighty, signaling the change in the wind and the coming storm, establishes the definite if still equivocal presence of a divine (or at least supernatural) force, but whether that force is the light itself is impossible to say. Most movies, eg A Serious Man, in which a character in one way or another grapples with a higher power, opt to leave the existence of that higher power open to interpretation. The reason may be that once you cross that line, and firmly establish the presence of an omnipotent puppet-master, as &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; does, the answer as to whose hands are pulling the strings becomes very real: The hands, of course, belong to the director.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Robert Eggers is the latest in a line of auteurs, most if not all male, who are famous for the demands they make of their actors. (Stanley Kubrick comes to mind as the quintessential example, and Alejandro Iñárritu earned his place in that pantheon with &lt;em&gt;The Revenant&lt;/em&gt;.) Kubrick’s now-infamous treatment of Shelley Duvall on the set of &lt;em&gt;The Shining&lt;/em&gt; was less self-evident, but with &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; it’s all there on the screen: Robert Pattinson struggling to shove a heavy wheelbarrow up a craggy slope as he’s pummeled with frigid seawater, Willem Dafoe choking on dirt as he’s buried alive, and so on. However honest their intentions, you can’t help but wonder if these directors get off to some subliminal extent on putting their actors through hell, and if we’re willing to do a little self-examination, we may see why. How often do we get to make real people into our playthings? To exercise over another person real and total control? The idea may be revolting, but since when has your subconscious ever cared about what you find revolting? Notwithstanding the existence or absence of such impulses within ourselves, we have to acknowledge that power dynamics like this–whether malicious, benevolent, or simply innate–play out every day: between parents and children, between employers and employees, between couples, between dictators and entire countries, between directors and actors, between Thomas Wake and Thomas Howard. The sadomasochistic trifecta formed by Dafoe, Pattinson, and Eggers is made more compelling by its alternative, which is difficult to imagine, and even harder to believe: A weary director soberly and solemnly torturing his performers to within an inch of their sanity, hating himself for it but nevertheless steadfast in his conviction that unjust though it may be, such treatment is essential to the story he’s trying to capture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But maybe it is essential. And maybe such a director does exist, or has existed. You could argue that the effect achieved, one of such palpable tension and burgeoning insanity, could not be evoked any other way. As to the physical torment the characters endure, how else do you show someone being buried alive other than to chuck them in a hole and throw dirt on them? In such a scene the line between the movie world and the real world blurs. The hallmark cinematic illusion succumbs to the understanding that what you’re watching is anything but illusive. You’re watching real-life person Willem Dafoe chew on dirt, and the effect is supremely unsettling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing then what the actors endured to bring this movie to life, the question of meaning, as addressed earlier, becomes paramount. The question is this: In the absence of any discernible meaning, how can we be sure &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; is anything more than one man’s meticulously crafted cathartic exercise in self-loathing and existential angst carried out vicariously via two piteous albeit willing actors, seemingly for no other reason than to make the pedantic point that suffering is inevitable? It’s not an appealing conclusion, not only because it wouldn’t be very interesting, but because the sheer vigor behind the film, practically radiating off the screen, demands that we make more of it than that. We have to believe that what the characters and the actors endured means something more, was in some way worth it. It’s a natural impulse, and one we can extrapolate to our own lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most of us would prefer to believe that all our hard work, all our pain, in some way matters. This belief embodies Thomas Howard to his core. In the confession scene, in which he “spills his beans,” Howard reveals that he is responsible for the death of Ephraim Winslow (Logan Hawkes), the foreman at his previous job. Thus we learn that he’s a man on the run from himself. He intends to remake himself anew, to wipe the slate clean by moving far away, taking on a new name and a new profession. He hopes to redeem himself through hard work and earn enough to buy his way into a new life of settled peace. But as the story progresses, it seems that everything on the island, from Wake to the sea itself, is determined to thwart his attempts at salvation. He is tested so relentlessly that we (and he) begin to wonder if he ever stood a chance at all. Wake, with his farts and self-important long-windedness, tests him. The one-eyed seabird, who rips at his pant-leg and outright attacks Howard at the cistern, tests him. Some force at large seems determined to keep the cistern itself unclean, forcing Howard to instead drink liquor, which counts as another strike against him. If the light is salvation, as Wake implies early in the movie, and salvation is to be earned, what does it mean if those attempts to earn it are continually and deliberately frustrated?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we see in the film, a man can only withstand such a direct assault on his inclination to uprightness for so long. Sooner or later, Howard has to break. By the time he kills Wake, he understands, as revealed by his discovery of Wake’s logbook, that all his efforts were for naught. His belief that his work matters–that is, that it will be rewarded–has been completely undermined. In the absence of that belief, or rather in the absence of the affirmation of that belief, life itself becomes pointless. And that’s where &lt;em&gt;The Lighthouse&lt;/em&gt; leaves us. In that bleak, barren place on the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded><category>horror</category><category>movies</category></item></channel></rss>